foreign
[Music]
healthier diets are associated with a
significantly lower risk of hearing loss
and for all three diet quality scoring
systems these researchers used avoidance
of meat was most strongly associated
with lower risk the bond from my last
video who preserved their hearing into
old age eight little meat but also
weren't eating sugary junk explaining
their almost total absence of dental
cavities a high glycemic diet of refined
carbs is also associated with developing
age-related hearing loss if it's the
blood sugar spikes that would explain
why diabetics and pre-diabetics are also
at higher risk
even among whole grains sorghum which is
the center of the bond diet has a
particularly low glycemic index due to
its resistant starch content costing
about a 25 lower rise in blood sugar
compared to whole wheat
impaired blood circulation may also
explain how noise damages the inner ear
as loud noises cause constriction of the
accompanying blood vessels this may also
help clarify the link between obesity
and hearing loss excess weight it may
just be a proxy for unhealthier diets
but the pro-inflammatory state of
obesity can itself lead to vascular
dysfunction measures of systemic
inflammation seem to directly correlate
with age-related hearing loss as do
measures of oxidative stress
in my video on brain inflammation I
introduced the antioxidant defense
activator Nerf 2 called guardian of
Health span and gatekeeper of species
longevity
those born with a genetic variant Nerf 2
that doesn't encode as well or
significantly more likely to develop
impaired hearing implicating the role of
free radicals in the process of hearing
loss
you can look in the back of people's
eyes and measure the amount of macular
pigment to the lutein and zeaxanthine
antioxidants concentrated in Greens and
correlate that with Superior hearing
the population data on antioxidant
intake and hearing loss is mixed though
take vitamin C for example some studies
show that higher vitamin C intake is
associated with better hearing but
others failed to find any significant
connection the only way to tell if
antioxidants help or not you know the
drill is to put them to the test adding
antioxidants to the diet of rats seems
to help prevent age-related rat hearing
loss but doing the same thing in mice
doesn't appear to help the most exciting
pre-clinical data may be a study in
which aged rats randomized to added
blueberries look like they had a
reversal in hearing deficits in fact
ending up better than the young rat oh
wait I thought hair cells don't
regenerate our ability to hear doesn't
just have to do with our ears but our
brain as we age our auditory cortex in
the temporal lobe of our brain loses
some of its ability to discriminate and
understand speech even in a quiet
environment we don't just need to sense
sounds but make sense out of them that's
where blueberries seem to come in
reversing the age-related cognitive
deficits in auditory processing but what
about in people their studies lacking
control groups that documented
improvements in hearing loss giving
people antioxidant supplements like
vitamins aec and alpha lipoic acid but
when properly put to the test in a
randomized deadline Placebo control
trial of a whole list of antioxidants
the supplements flopped no effect on any
of the measured hearing aspects is there
any supplement that's been shown to help
with hearing in older adults yes
folic acid the supplement form of folate
from concentrated in beans and greens
some observational studies had found
that higher levels of folate in the
blood seem to correlate with better
hearing but maybe that's just a marker
of eating a healthier diet in general so
Dutch researchers set out on an
ambitious three-year double-blind
placebo-controlled trial randomizing
more than 700 older men and women to
take 800 micrograms of folic acid a day
or an indistinguishable Placebo
excitingly those who have been taking
the folic acid suffered significantly
less decline in hearing its speech
frequencies the effect size was rather
small so I said one might expect a
proportion of men for example who would
be hearing aid candidates at age 75
might drop from 33 percent to 22 with
folic acid supplementation also note the
study was done in the Netherlands where
at the time the food supply was not
fortified with folic acid in the U.S
with folic acid fortification has been
mandated in refined grain products for
decades it's unclear how much additional
benefits supplements might add
regardless the healthiest sources are
dark green leafy vegetables and legumes
a cup of cooked lentil says 90 of adult
daily needs
[Music]
foreign